A Guide to the Clement Dixon Johnston Papers, 1939-1979 (Bulk 1942-1962)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Clement Dixon Johnston Papers, 1939-1979 (Bulk, 1942-1962)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1982-012
19.0 cu. ft. 19 boxes
The collection contains correspondence, speeches, scrapbooks, diaries, photographs, and other memorabilia from Johnston's tenure and local and national politics and business.
Johnston, Clement Dixon, 1895-1979
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Clement Dixon Johnston Papers were donated to Virginia Tech University Libraries in 1982.
Biographical Note
Clement Dixon Johnston (1895-1979), a native of Louisville, Kentucky, graduated from Centre College in 1916. He began a career in business and public affairs in 1926 when he founded the Roanoke (Virginia) Public Warehouse. Johnston served at various times as president of the Roanoke Chamber of Commerce (1934), deputy director of the U.S. Office of Civil Defense Planning (1947-1948), president of the U.S. Chamber of Commerce (1954-1955), and special representative of the U.S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee to study the foreign aid program in Southeast Asia (1956-1967). In 1960, he served as president of the Virginia State Chamber of Commerce.
During World War I, Johnston served as an Infantry Captain and Company Commander in the Panama Canal Zone. He retained reserve status until accepting a World War II assignment. He was Warehouse Officer for the Army Ordinance Field Service for nearly three years. Johnston completed his war service in China as Ordinance Supply Officer and Staff Quartermaster for "Z" forces under General Stillwell.
Scope and Content
Johnston's papers include correspondence, speeches, letterbooks, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, diaries, photographs, and memorabilia from his local and national business, political, and military careers. The majority of the collection consists of subject files (especially Johnston's service with the U.S. Chamber of Commerce and foreign aid work) and correspondence.
Arrangement
The collection is in its original order.
Boxes 1-9 and 12 include subject files in alphabetical order. Boxes 9-11 contain speeches from local and national events. Boxes 13-16 include correspondence, arranged chronologically. Box 17 contains military materials, honors and awards, and photographs. Box 18 includes publications. Boxes 18-19 contains scrapbooks.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South
Contents List
- Subject Files
  - AWA (American Warehousemen's Association), 1942-1952; Advisory Committee, Office of Defense Transportation; Air Force Seminar, 1949; American Association of Nurserymen, 1955; American Chain of Warehouses, 1942-1949; American Petroleum Institute; Boy Scouts of America; Boys Club of America; Colleges and Universities (Centre, VMI, VPI, UVA); Hospital Fund Development; Burrell Memorial Hospital, 1942-1958. (Box 1)
  - Burrell Memorial Hospital, 1959-1961; Community Hospital; Jefferson Lewis-Gale; McVitty House; Junior Achievement; Modern Arts Club; Monroe Library & Foundation; Rotary International; Sales Executives Club; Politics (Important letters, Democrats for Nixon, Goldwater-Byrd, Nixon-Lodge); Port Terminal Investigation; State Department; Taber Committee (Congress), 1953; Poly-Scientific Corporation; Travel (1955 State Department tour of Australia, India, and other Pacific countries; 1960; Argentina Trip, 1961; 1964-1-65; 1971-1972; 1975). (Box 2)
  - Rotary International; Roanoke Chamber of Commerce; Virginia State Chamber of Commerce, 1942-1960. (Box 3)
  - Virginia State Chamber of Commerce, 1960-1962; Virginia State Chamber of Commerce, 1962-1975; U.S. Chamber of Commerce--Conference of National Organizations. (Box 4)
  - U.S. Chamber of Commerce--Conference of National Organizations; U.S. Chamber of Commerce--Foreign Affairs Committee (Australia, New Zealand, India, Pakistan, 1955-1956; Southeast Asia, 1956-1957; Testimony before the U.S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee); Government documents relating to foreign aid ( see list below); U.S. Chamber of Commerce, 1942-1950 (Committee on International Political & Social Problems, Southeastern Division of U.S. Chamber of Commerce--Washington, D.C. and Atlanta, GA offices). (Box 5)
    Scope and Content
    List of government documents relating to foreign aid
    January 1957
    The Objectives of U.S. Economic Assistance Programs
    February 1957
    Greece, Turkey, and Iran
    No. 2: Personnel for the Mutual Security Program
    No. 7: American Private Enterprise, Foreign Economic Development, and teh Aid Programs
    March 1957
    No. 3: The Role of Foreign Aid in the Development of Other Countries
    No. 4: The Use of Private Contractors in Foreign Aid Programs
    No. 7: Southeast Asia (Vietnam, Thailand, Cambodia, Laos, Burma, and Indonesia)
    May 1957
    Foreign Aid--Report of the Special Committee to Study the Foreign Aid Program
  - U.S. Chamber of Commerce, 1946-1952 (Southeastern Division; International Chamber of Commerce, 1945-19446; Young Men's Committee; William K. Jackson, president, 1946-1947; Eric A. Johnston, president, 1945-1946; Finance Budget & Audit; Committee on International Political & Social Problems); U.S. Chamber of Commerce, 1948-1954 (Circle X; Commission on Intergovernmental Relations; Congressional Study; Civil Defense; National Automobile Dealers' Association); U.S. Chamber of Commerce (Armed Forces Manpower Committee; Arch Booth; Ralph Bradford; Brookings Institution; Canada-U.S. Committee; Defense Production Act; Federal Surplus Relief Corporation; Foreign Aid; Government Expenditures). (Box 6)
  - U.S. Chamber of Commerce (Military Spending Committee; Universal Military Training; International Political & Social Committee; Political Committee; Policy Committee/Nominating Committee; President Seyferth); U.S. Chamber of Commerce, 1952-1955 (including congratulatory letters); U.S. Chamber of Commerce, 1955-1960. (Box 7)
  - U.S. Chamber of Commerce, 1956-1959; U.S. Chamber of Commerce, 1961, including Circle X. (Box 8)
  - U.S. Chamber of Commerce--Project Adequate Roads. (Box 9)
  - Trade Associations, including: Merchandise Warehousing Code Authority (Minneapolis; Chicago; Savannah, GA; Dallas; Seattle; Fort Worth; Boston); Commercial Code--Virginia (National--minutes, by-laws, proceedings, complaint hearings; National Recovery Administration; Newspaper Clippings; Southern Warehousemen's Association--1935 convention, proxy to vote, list of subscribers; D.L. Tilly; Clover Farm Stores, 1935; W. M. Caudell; Frank M. Cole; Lorena W. Coop; A. Lane Cricher; R. G. Culbertson; Distribution Warehousing; J. F. Duffy; Elmer Erickson; Miscellaneous. (Box 12)
- Speeches
  - Speeches--loose-leaf notebooks. (Box 9)
  - Speeches--large loose-leaf notebook, miscellaneous manuscript and typescript notes; Speeches identified by "Title," subject, or site of delivery ( see list below). (Box 10)
    List of identified speeches
    "Alternative Pathways"
    "America's Priceless Heritage - The Competitive System"
    Armed Forces
    Australian Broadcasting Commission
    Bar Association
    "Boundless Business Frontiers"
    Business
    Business & Industry
    "Centers of Initiative"
    Chamber of Commerce
    Civic Affairs
    Democracy - Citizenship
    Democratic National Committee
    Economics - "Pathways to Progress"
    Education - Colleges & Universities
    Foreign Aid
    Free Enterprise
    "Go South Young Man"
    Hibernian Society
    Hospitals
    Industrial Editors
    Keynote
    London
    Middle Man ("Jobber")
    Minimum Wage Law
    National Affairs
    "The New Renaissance"
    Ohio State Chamber of Commerce
    Orlando Chamber of Commerce
    "Pathways to Progress"
    "Price Controls" [a recording]
    Public Housing
    "Rendezvous with Destiny"
    Right to Work
    Testimony
    Transportation - Roads
    "Unaware and Unalert"
    Welfare State
    World-International Leadership
  - Numerous legal pads filled with handwritten notes and rough drafts. Many editorial references (clippings, brochures, etc.). (Box 11)
- Correspondence
  - General Correspondence, 1942-1950. (Box 12)
  - General Correspondence, 1950, 1951. (Box 13)
  - General Correspondence, 1952, 1953. (Box 14)
  - General Correspondence, 1953, 1954-1955, 1955-1957. (Box 15)
  - General Correspondence, 1958-1960, 1961, 1962-1964. (Box 16)
  - General Correspondence, 1964-1979. (Box 17)
- Memorabilia (Honors, Photographs, Scrapbooks)
  - Military (Diaries, 1942-1943; Legion of Merit correspondence); Honorary degrees; Photographs. (Box 17)
  - Scrapbook: Hospital fund drive. (Box 18)
  - Scrapbooks: 3 covering U.S. Chamber of Commerce presidential year, 1954-1955; Roanoke Campaign for Refugee and Overseas Relief, 1939 (includes a 12-minute sermonette); The story of "Alternative Pathways," 1952. (Box 19)
- Publications and Clippings
  - Chamber of Commerce programs, policies, directories; Government documents ( see list below); Magazine articles ( see list below); Miscellaneous publications ( see list below); Newspaper clippings. (Box 18)
    Government documents
    How the Tax Rate Reform Would Benefit You (Herlong-Baker bills)
    1963 Congressional Handbook
    Under the Dome--How Our Congress Works
    Page from June 16, 1959 Congressional Recor d
    A Study of Civil Defense, 1948
    Civil Defense for National Security, OCDP, 1948
    The Federal Budget in Brief (FY1956)
    Overlapping Taxes in the United States
    Magazine articles
    Newsweek, May 10, 1954, p. 77
    Newsweek, February 28, 1955, p. 26
    Washington Report, May 7, 1954
    Washington Report, May 13, 1955
    Manufacturers Record, April 1955, p. 41
    Florida Motor Court Journal, November 1954
    The Commonwealth Magazine of Virginia, May 1954
    Nation's Business, June 1954, p. 38
    Illustrated Weekly of Pakistan, September 4, 1955, p. 9
    Miscellaneous
    American Association of Commerce Publications
    American Warehousemen's Association program
    Washington (D.C.) Trade Association Executives membership list, 1954
    The American Forum, April 24, 1955--"Women Want to Know"
    "The Economics of the Guaranteed Wage"
    "'Fringe' Benefits"